Guide to the Bill Walter Studio Photographs circa 1890-1978
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Bill Walter Studio Photographs
circa 1890-1978
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
PC 120
Walter, Bill.
39 Linear feet of shelf space 39 Boxes
Collection of photographs from the Bill Walter Studio, Colfax, Washington. The bulk of the collection is safety film negatives, but it also contains many photographs, some oversize and panoramic.
Bill Walter was born on November 4, 1915 in Pullman, WA. He lived in a number of locations in Washington State, graduating from Ballard High School in Seattle. He attended the State College of Washington shortly before World War II, where he met and married Mary Sands. Mr. Walter joined the National Guard in 1940, and was assigned to one of the first units to be nationalized.
In the National Guard, he served in the medical core, rising to the rank of Colonel by the time the war ended. After the war, he located his family in Colfax, Washington and started a sporting goods and photography business. As the years went by, he shifted more and more toward photography. On several occasions, he attended photography school in Winona, Indiana.
Mr. Walter advertised himself as the "Photography on the Palouse". Many of his photographs appeared in the local newspaper, the Colfax Gazette, and at one time a large display of his work was exhibited in Colfax City Hall. Mr. Walter retired in 1979 but continued his photography until the early 1990's. He passed away on November 15, 1999.
Collection of photographs from the Bill Walter Studio, Colfax, Washington. The bulk of the collection is safety film negatives, but it also contains many photographs, some oversize and panoramic.
Highlights of the collection include a glass plate negative of the former Colfax Courthouse (torn down in the 1950's), a plethora of images depicting Palouse agriculture, both early and early modern farm machinery, local businesses, and calamities such as the Oakesdale Grain Growers Elevator Fire in 1970 and the Colfax Floods of 1910 and 1948. Of a more regional interest are the Construction of the Boundary Dam for Seattle City Light Company in 1967 and the 12th World Jamboree of the Boy Scouts of America held in Farragut State Park in 1967.
The collection is arranged in 4 series, primarily by format. Where possible, the original order used by Mr. Walter is preserved. The major exceptions to this are Series 1, Photograph Subject Files and Series 2, Photograph Negative Subject Files. These two series reflect a subject arrangement designed to make the collection more easily accessible.
Series 1 contains photographs, mostly 8x10, depicting various scenes and subjects, mostly of regional interest.
Series 2 is also a series of subject files, black and white, most of which are of a local history nature.
Series 3, almost entirely portraits of individuals, families, weddings, etc., forms the bulk of the collection.
Series 4 contains oversize photographs, panoramic photographs and some photographs that could not be identified by subject or place. Many of these photographs are copies made by Walter from other photographers.
This collection is open and available for research use.
B. Oliver Walter donated this collection to the Washington State University Libraries in 2000 (UPC-0014) and in 2020 (MS.2020.07). On Feb. 12, 2021, 15 photographs were gifted to MASC by the Whitman County Library, which had received them one month prior from Oliver Walter of Laramie, WY (who had acquired them while living in Colfax), and these were interfiled as folder 8 in box 1. The former folders 8 to 13 in that box were renumbered 9 to 14 at that time.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Boundary Hydroelectric Project -- History -- Photographs.; St. Ignatius Hospital (Colfax, Wash.) -- History -- Photographs.
Colfax (Wash.) -- History -- Photographs.; Whitman County (Wash.) -- History -- Photographs.
Wheat -- Harvesting -- History -- Photographs.; Steamboats -- History -- Photographs.; Floods -- Washington (State) -- Whitman County -- History -- Photographs.; Ranches -- Washington (State) -- Whitman County -- Photographs.
Washington (State); Agriculture; City and Town Life; Photographs
- Series 1: Photographs Subject Files, circa 1920-1978
  - Early Colfax, circa 1900-1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Palouse Region Small Towns
    - Early Elberton, Washington, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - St. John, Washington, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Winona, Washington, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Oakesdale, Washington, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Moscow, Idaho, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Potlatch, Idaho, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Thornton, Washington, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boundary Dam Construction, 1967, 28 photos and negatives (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Boundary Dam Construction, 1967, 44 photos, some duplicates (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 12th Boy Scout World Jamboree, Farragut State Park, Idaho (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Palouse Empire Fair: Exhibits, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Palouse Empire Fair: Rodeo, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Protests in Colfax, likely Feb. 28, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fire, Oakesdale Grain Growers Elevator, 1970, 12 photos, includes negatives (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Palouse Highway (US 195) Aerial Views, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Tanker Truck Accident on the Palouse, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Rock Creek Park (color photographs and negatives), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Central Ferry Barge Loading, circa 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Central Ferry Barge Loading, circa 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series 2: Photograph Negatives Subject Files, 1948-1988
  - Agriculture
    - Steiger Farm Cattle, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ensley Children and Cattle, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ensley Bull, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Immler (sp?), G., Cattle, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Sauer, Horse Ranches and Harvest, 1961, 5 color negatives (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - McGregor Ranch, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Harry Sandeen Farm, Harvest, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mykelbust Ranch, Harvest, 1954 and 1955, 22 photos (6 from 1955, 16 from 1954) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Oscar Steiger Farm, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Marlo Ochs Ranch, Harvest, 1954, 11 photos (1954) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Dave White Ranch, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Townsend Harvest, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Heusle Ranch, Harvest, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - R. Farr Ranch, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - John Divine Ranch, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Russell Looney Ranch, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Colyar Ranch, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Jeffries Farm Harvest (Dean Upshaw), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Koenig Harvest, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Otto Camp Harvest, 1953, 1957, 12 photographs (7 from 1953, 5 from 1957) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Del Flewring(sp?) Ranch, Harvest (Case farm machinery), undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Moore Farm, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Hensle Farm, Harvest, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Lloyd Och Ranch, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Other Miscellaneous Harvest Negatives (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Harvest and Harvest Machines (slides), circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Palouse Region Events
    - Colfax (Whitman County) Courthouse (glass plate), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - City view of Colfax, circa 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Colfax Flood, 1948, 40 photographs; roll film negatives (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Elberton Flood, 1963">1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Mud in Front of Studio", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Negro Demonstration", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Palouse Empire Fair, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Bill Walter Studio, fish and game catches, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Planting" fish (Palouse River?), 1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Fire, Endsley Flowers and Gifts, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Fire, Henry Building (Colfax?), 1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Palouse Countryside, Aerial and Ground Views, 1968; Macguire, 1968; Meyers, 1970, 87 photographs (64 Palouse, 23 Meyers), 7 color negatives (Macguire) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Colfax Aerial Views, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Palouse Region Aviation, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Palouse Region Small Towns:
    - Eastern Wash. Natural Gas Co.-Map of Endicott, Washington, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Garfield Elevator, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Thornton panorama, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Palouse Region Churches/Church Buildings
    - Colfax Lutheran Choir, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - St. John Lutheran Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Endicott Adventist Church, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - St. John Christian Church, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - St. John Catholic Church, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Garfield Nazarene Church, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Ewan Nazarene Church, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - St. John Catholic Church, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Palouse Region Schools
    - Joint Picnic, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 8th Grade Graduation (school unidentified), group photo, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 5th Grade, St. John, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 4th Grade, Endicott, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 4th Grade, St. John, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 3rd Grade, Palouse, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 4th Grade, Oakesdale, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 2nd Grade, Garfield, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 1st Grade, Garfield, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 2nd. Grade, Rosalia, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 3rd Grade Field Trip, Endicott, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Palouse Region Businesses
    - Swanson Spray Company, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Palouse Ammonia, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - McGregor Chemical, Steptoe Pea Plant, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Rogers Bros. Seed Co, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Monsanto Co, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Richfield Oil Co/Brown and Holter (Pullman?), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - R.A. Hanson Co., Palouse, WA, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Les" Mills Aircraft, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - LaCrosse Grain Growers, Dusty Elevator, circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Colfax Businesses/Bldgs
    - Russell Bartlett Trucking Co, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 195 Café/ B.P.O.E, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - LaVerne Bakery, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Colfax Welding, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Colfax City Shop, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Gr. Grow Building, construction, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Stueckle-Franz Bldg, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Seattle 1st National Bank (includes negatives), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Brown and Holter (car dealership), opening, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Burgunder Bldg, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Disposal Plant, concreting, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Tom Gallagher Garage, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Wheatland Marina, Grand Opening, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Telephone Bldg construction, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Port of Whitman, Central Ferry Barge Loading, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Port of Whitman, Central Ferry Elevator, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Port of Whitman, Central Ferry, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Western Grain Exchange, Central Ferry, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Historic Structures/Buildings
    - Old National Bank, Interior, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Elberton Bridge, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - St. Ignatius Hospital and Catholic Chapel, 1960-1966, 29 items; includes photographs (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Whitman Hotel, 1977, 4 color photos and negatives (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Community Services Organizations
    - Whitman County Sheriff and Crew, 1957-1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Colfax Police Dept, 1963, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Colfax Fire Dept, 1922, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pullman Fire Dept, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Port of Whitman, Lower Granite Lock and Dam Project Map, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Helena Duncan Crime Scene, November 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Palouse Region Negatives
    - Elks Style Show, 1974 (color negatives) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - State Class D Basketball Tournament (St. John vs. Davenport), 1962 St. John Basketball Team, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Colfax Junior Miss (color photos and negatives), undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Whitman County Bar Assn, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Jenetta Morris, Easter Seals, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Ed Curtis poster on Post Office billboard, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Carol Steuckle, lentil products, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Washington Water Power-new truck with Ed Stone, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Pinski singing, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Baumiter (sp?) figurines, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Solar eclipse, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "New Hiway", 1956 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "Historical Society", 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Empire Title Co., Pullman - College Hill Map, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Series 3: Portraits, 1950-1978
  - Miscellaneous Portraits: weddings, "photos never picked up", portraits, 1950's-1961, C-L (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Portraits, 1950's-1961, L-Z (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Portraits, 1958-1961; more weddings, 1950-1961 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Portraits, 1958-1961; servicemen's portraits (Box 8)
  - Portraits, 1960-1961, A-M (Box 9)
  - Portraits, 1962, A-R (Box 10)
  - Portraits, 1962, R-Z; 1963 A-E (Box 11)
  - Portraits, 1963, F-S (Box 12)
  - Portraits, 1963, S-Z; Miscellaneous Portraits, 1960-1970 (Box 13)
  - Portraits, 1964, A-H (Box 14)
  - Portraits, 1964, H-S (Box 15)
  - Portraits, 1964, S-Z; 1965, A-K (Box 16)
  - Portraits, 1965, K-Z; 1966, A (Box 17)
  - Portraits, 1966, B-O (Box 18)
  - Portraits, 1966, P-Z; 1967, A-H (Box 19)
  - Portraits, 1967, H-Z; 1968, A-E (Box 20)
  - Portraits, 1968, E-M (Box 21)
  - Portraits, 1968, N-Z; 1969, A-D (Box 22)
  - Portraits, 1969, D-W (Box 23)
  - Portraits, 1970, A-S (Box 24)
  - Portraits, 1970, S-Z; 1971, A-L (Box 25)
  - Portraits, 1971, L-Z; 1972, A-C (Box 26)
  - Portraits, 1972, D-M (Box 27)
  - Portraits, 1972, M-Z; 1973, A-B (Box 28)
  - Portraits, 1973, C-O (Box 29)
  - Portraits, 1973, P-Z and miscellaneous photos (Box 30)
  - Portraits, 1974, A-K (Box 31)
  - Portraits, 1974, K-Z (Box 32)
  - Portraits, 1975, A-U (Box 33)
  - Portraits, 1975, V-Z; 1976, A-R (Box 34)
  - Portraits, 1976, R-Z; 1977, A-H (Box 35)
  - Portraits, 1977, H-Z; 1978, A-Z (Box 36)
- Series 4: Oversize and Unidentified Photographs
  - Miscellaneous Photographs
    - Early Palouse Agriculture, undated (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Early Modern Palouse Agriculture, undated (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Colfax Flood, 1910 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Early Modern Colfax, undated (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Steamboats, undated (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Identified
    - Union Pacific Railroad (town unknown), undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Pupils of District 166, 1909 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Central Ferry, Barge Loading, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Whitman County Bar Association, 1973 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Rev. Cushing Eels, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Dr. W.A. Mitchell (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Spalding at Almota, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Railroad being built in Lamont (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - L.L. Druning and friends, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Cashup Davis funeral, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Deed to City of Colfax, 1874 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Portraits Unidentified (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Unidentified (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - 1948 Flood (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Panoramic Photographs
    - I.L. Moore Header, 1913 (Hutchison Photo, undated) (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Central Ferry Bridge Celebration, 1924 (Hutchison Photo) (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Diamond, Washington (Allen Photo Co., Walla Walla), undated (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Diamond, Washington (Hutchison Photo, undated), undated (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Steptoe, Washington, undated (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Stueckle and Broekel Thresher (Hutchison Photo), 1913 (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Colfax, Washington, undated (Box 38 o.s.)
    - Miscellaneous Unidentified Panoramic Photographs (Box 38 o.s.)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs
    - Palouse Agriculture (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - “Near Rosalia Wash” (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - Palouse People and Structures (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Landscape Photographs (Box 39, Folder 4)